Guide to the Robert Broughton Papers, 1965-1977 AIS.1977.42
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Robert Broughton Papers
1965-1977
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Broughton, Robert
AIS.1977.42
11.25 Linear Feet (9 boxes)
The collection of Robert Broughton, a Duquesne University Law Professor active in environmental conservation and air pollution control issues in Allegheny County, contains correspondence, research, reports, and publications concerning local government and environmental law.
Biography
Robert Broughton, a Duquesne University Law Professor, actively participated in environmental conservation and air pollution control issues in Allegheny County. He joined Duquesne University in 1966 and became a full professor three years later. Broughton chaired the Allegheny County Board of Air Pollution Appeals and Variance Review, April 1970 - February 1973. He also served as chair of the Land Use Policy Committee of the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania. Broughton's father, Philip S. Broughton, some of whose papers appear in this collection, served as a former vice chairman of the Allegheny County Board of Health.
Robert Broughton died on August 1, 1977, at the age of 42, while climbing Nanga Parbat, a mountain in Pakistan. An experienced climber, he participated in the climb along with others from the Pittsburgh Explorers' Club.
Scope and Content Notes
The papers of Robert Broughton consist of records dating from 1965 - 1977, and have been organized into 8 series: Subject Files, Citizen's Advisory Council to the Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Resources, Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Resources Environmental Quality Board, Correspondence, Manuscript Notes, Unpublished research papers and reports, Local Environmental Organizations and Environmental Law, and Publications. More information about the records is available at the individual series level. The Broughton Papers mainly concentrate on environmental issues affecting Pittsburgh and Allegheny County. Publications of mainly local and regional nature have been retained in the collection.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Suzanne Broughton, wife of Robert Broughton, 1977.
Previous Citation
Robert Broughton Papers, 1965-1977, AIS.1977.42, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Robert Broughton Papers, 1965-1977, AIS 77:42, Archives of Industrial Society, University of Pittsburgh
Human ecology -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Environmental sciences -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Air quality management -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Air -- Pollution -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Pollution control personnel -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Environment; Personal papers; Allegheny County (Pa.). Bureau of Air Pollution Control; Broughton, Robert
- Subject Files, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Contains correspondence of the Allegheny County Bureau of Air Pollution Control retarding legal action against such Pittsburgh businesses as Duquesne Light (with emphasis on the Davis Power Project), Fort Pitt Steel Casting, and Jones Laughlin Steel Corporation. Other correspondence includes the Bureau's response to a state proposal to develop Rt. 801 at Sinnemahoning Creek, miscellaneous correspondence, and press releases.
  - Abrasive Metals Compay (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Allegheny County Steam Heating (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Armour Company (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Armstrong Cork Company (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Blaw Knox Foundry Mill Machinery, Inc. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Duquesne Light (Box 1, Folder 6-22)
  - Fort Pitt Steel Casting (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - General Electric (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - H.J. Heinz Company (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Jones Laughlin Steel Corporation (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
  - Keystone Casting Supply Co. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Lois Hahn Sons (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - O.Hommel Company (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Pittoon (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Pittsburgh Barrell and Drum Co. (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Pram (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Shenango, Inc (Box 2, Folder 34-36)
  - U.S. Steel (Box 2, Folder 37-41)
  - Westinghouse Electric Corp (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Allegheny County Bureau of Air Pollution Control (Box 2, Folder 43-47)
- Citizen's Advisory Council to the Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Resources, 1969 - 1977, II.
  Contains minutes, correspondence and memos, various reports and testimonies, including annual reports, 1971-1972 and 1973-1974, and Office of State Planning and Development publications on land policy, adjudications of the Environmental Hearing Board, newsclippings, and miscellanea.
  - Minutes, November 8, 1971-April 16, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 46-56)
  - Correspondence and Memos, July 15, 1971-June17, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 57-61)
  - Reports and Testimonies (Box 3, Folder 62-68)
- Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Resources Environmental Quality Board, 1972, III. (Box 4)
  Contains regulations, agenda and minutes, fact sheets, and statements made to the Environmental Quality Board by the League of Women Voters.
  - Reports and Testimonies (Box 4, Folder 69-75)
  - Annual Reports, 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Adjucations of the Environmental Hearing Board (Box 4, Folder 77-87)
  - Newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - Citizen's Advisory Council to the Department of Environmental Resources--Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Environmental Quality Board (Box 4, Folder 90)
- Correspondence, IV. (Box 5)
  Contains personal correspondence with the National Forestry Service about the Monongahela National Forest, and several letters from U.S. Congressmen and Senators including Rep. Robert J. Corbett, Rep. H. John Heinz, III, Rep. John P. Saylor, and Sen. Hugh Scott.
  - Air Pollution Commission of Pennsylvania (Box 5, Folder 91-93)
  - Environmental Groups--By-laws and Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - Robert Broughton--Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - Monongahela National Forest (Box 5, Folder 96)
- Manuscript Notes, V.
  This series includes a folder of Broughton's personal writings and handwritten notes on a variety of topics. Also included are drafts of papers by Broughton and drafts and proposals written by his father, Philip S. Broughton..
  - Robert Broughton--Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 97)
  - Robert Broughton--Notes (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - Research Papers and Reports (Box 5, Folder 99-100)
  - Philip Broughton: Drafts and Memos (Box 5, Folder 101)
- Unpublished Research Papers and Reports, VI.
  Copies of research papers given at various conferences.
  - Research Papers and Reports (Box 5, Folder 102-119)
  - Research Papers and Reports (Box 6, Folder 120-157)
- Local Environmental Organizations and Environmental Law, VII.
  Series VII contains local government reports, along with the rules and regulations for air pollution emissions in Allegheny County, and the by-laws of many local environmental organizations. This series also contains transcripts and other court documents from various environmentally related cases. The court documents include reports of hearings of the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania House of Representative's Special Committee on Pesticide Control from 1970, and transcripts of cases involving groups or organizations such as the Pennsylvania Environmental Council, National Helium Corporation, Environmental Defense Fund, Department of Housing and Urban Development, United States Steel Corporation, Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, County of Allegheny,the United States of America, Natural Resources Defense Council, Natural Lands Trust, the Texas Committee on Natural Resources, Manufacturers Light and Heat Company, Raccoon Valley Conservation Association, and several local labor unions. Copies of rules and regulations of the Allegheny County Health Department regarding air pollution and the Air Management and Air Pollution Control Regulations and Amendments can also be found in this series.
  - Air Management and Air Pollution Control Regulations and Amendments--Philadelphia, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 158)
  - Air Pollution Commission of Pennsylvania--Rules and Regulations Concerning Air Pollution, 1969-1973 (Box 7, Folder 159)
  - Local Government Reports--Allegheny County Health Department Rules and Regulations Concerning Air Pollution, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 160)
  - Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, County of Allegheny VS US Steel Corporation (Box 7, Folder 161)
  - Commonwealth of Pennsylvania House of Representatives Special Committee on Pesticide Control (Box 7, Volume 1-5)
  - Duquesne University of the Holy Ghost and General Teamsters, Chauffers and Helpers Local 249 and Employees Committee of Duquesne University (Box 7, Folder 162)
  - Environmental Defense Fund Inc. VS Hoerner Waldorf Corporation (Box 7, Folder 163)
  - Germantown Community Council VS Department of Housing and Urban Development (Box 7, Folder 164)
  - Mrs. Cyril G. Fox and Natural Lands Trust (Box 7, Folder 165)
  - Natural Helium Corporation VS Rogers C.B. Morton (Box 7, Folder 166)
  - Natural Resources Defense Council VS Environmental Protection Agency (Box 7, Folder 167)
  - Paul H. Stitt and Loretta Stitt VS Manufacturer's Light and Heat Company (Box 7, Folder 168)
  - Pennsylvania Environmental Council (Box 7, Folder 169-173)
  - Pennsylvania Environmental Council (Box 8, Folder 174)
  - Proposed Ambient Air Quality Standards (Box 8, Folder 175)
  - Raccoon Valley Conservation Association (Box 8, Folder 176)
  - Robert Parker VS United States of America (Box 8, Folder 177)
  - Texas Committee on Natural Resources VS Pearce Johnson (Box 8, Folder 178)
  - Texas Committee on Natural Resources VS United States of America (Box 8, Folder 179)
  - United States of America VS Blue Bell Incorporated and Genesco Incorporated (Box 8, Folder 180)
  - United States of America VS Garage Door Manufacturers Association, Incorporated (Box 8, Folder 181)
  - United States of America VS Multiple Listing Service (Box 8, Folder 182)
  - United States of America VS Overhead Door Distributors Association of Greater Delaware Valley (Box 8, Folder 183)
  - Court Transcripts and Related Documents--Miscellaneous (Box 8, Folder 184)
- Publications, VIII.
  Published reports concerning local governments and various environmentally related pamphlets, periodicals and newsletters.
  - Pamphlets (Box 8, Folder 185)
  - Battelle Research Outlook "Cleaning up the Atmosphere," Volume 2, Number 3, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 186)
  - Central Atlantic Environmental News, February 26, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 187)
  - Conservation Foundation, 1969-1971 (Box 8, Folder 188)
  - Enviromap, 1975-1977 (Box 8, Folder 189)
  - Environmental Action, 1970, 1972, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 190)
  - Environmental Defense, 1970-1977 (Box 8, Folder 191)
  - Environmental Science and Technology, June 1970 (Box 8, Folder 192)
  - Highlands Voice, 1976-1979 (Box 8, Folder 193)
  - Minerals and Materials, July 1976 (Box 8, Folder 194)
  - Open Space Reports, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 195)
  - Rocky Mountain Mineral Law Newsletter, June 1970 (Box 8, Folder 196)
  - SIPI Report, Fall 1970 (Box 8, Folder 197)
  - Social Climber, Winter 1967 (Box 8, Folder 198)
  - West Virginia Highlands Conservancy (Box 8, Folder 199)
  - Wilderness Society, June 5, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 200)
  - Miscellaneous Articles on Steel Plant Facilities and Furnaces (Box 8, Folder 201)
  - Federal Power Commission and Publications List and a Glossary of Important Power and Rate Terms (Box 8, Folder 202)
  - Historical Analysis of the Region, Southwestern Pennsylvania Regional Planning Commission (Box 8, Volume 1)
  - Housing in Southwestern Pennsylvania: A summary of Problems and Progress, Southwestern Pennsylvania Regional Planning Commission (Box 8, Volume 2)
  - Key Elements of the Allegheny County Land Development Program, County of Allegheny (Box 8, Volume 3)
  - Laurel Hill Study (Box 8, Volume 4)
  - Park and Recreation Guide, Venango County (Box 8, Volume 5)
  - Plan of Operations: Neighborhood Urban Extension, Pittsburgh, ACTION-Housing, Inc. (Box 8, Volume 6)
  - Surface Mining and Our Environment, U.S. Department of the Interior (Box 8, Volume 7)
  - Venango Corridor Urban Beautification Study, Venango County (Box 8, Volume 8)
  - Venango County Interchange Study (Box 8, Volume 9)
  - Your Government and the Environment, Matthew J. Kerbec (Box 8, Volume 10)